Guide to the Alice Raphael Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alice Raphael Papers
1917-1977
YCGL MSS 21
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11
(23 boxes) + 1 art object
The Alice Raphael Papers contain writings, translations, correspondence, lectures, photographs, a scrapbook and other papers that document the professional and personal life of author and translator Alice Raphael. The papers include letters from Carl Gustav Jung and drafts of Raphael's book Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust' and her translation of Goethe's Faust: A Tragedy Part One and Faust: A Tragedy Part Two. The papers span the years 1918-1977.
Raphael, Alice, 1887-1975
Faust; a tragedy: in a modern translation by Alice Raphael.
Goethe and the Philosophers Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and in the Second Part of 'Faust' by Alice Raphael
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice Raphael, 1963, 1966, 1969. Gift of Alice Wolff, 1975.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 23 contains audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Alice Raphael (1887-1975)
Alice Pearl Raphael was born on June 22, 1887 in Brownsville, Texas. She attended Barnard College in New York City and studied music in Germany. Raphael later lived in Zurich and studied with Carl Gustav Jung and Fritz Wittels and was a lay analyst for several years. Raphael focused for many years on her translation of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe's Faust: A Tragedy Part One and Faust: A Tragedy Part Two. Her friend William A. Speck, curator of his own collection at Yale University's Collection of German Literature, assisted her in the translation until his death in 1928. Carl Schreiber, who oversaw the Speck Collection following Speck's death, befriended Raphael and continued assistance with her translations. In 1939, Raphael met Curt von Faber du Faur, who in 1944 became curator of Yale's Collection of German Literature and university faculty member. Raphael and Faber du Faur were close colleagues and friends until Faber du Faur died in 1966.
Raphael published several articles, reviews, and the 1965 book Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust'. This book analyses Goethe in the context of Jungian theory. In the 1920s, Raphael was interested in drawing and studied drawing in Washington, CT. She preferred colored pencils and expressed herself through a method that she called "spontaneous creative expression."
Raphael lived in Manhattan for most of her life, where she founded the Analytical Psychology Club of New York and was an active member of the Society for Psychical Research. She married Henry Eckstein in 1911 and had two daughters. Raphael died in Manhattan on August 27, 1975.
Scope and Contents
The Alice Raphael Papers contain writings, translations, correspondence, lectures, photographs, a scrapbook and other papers that document the professional and personal life of author and translator Alice Raphael. Writings and translations comprise the bulk of the papers. Raphael's writings include drafts for her book Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust.' The papers contain several drafts of Raphael's translation of Goethe's Faust: A Tragedy Part One and Two with annotations and notes that reveal her translation process. Correspondence primarily consists of correspondence with Carl Gustav Jung, William A. Speck, Curt von Faber du Faur, and other curators of the Yale Collection of German Literature. The bulk of the correspondence regards her work to publish her Goethe translation and her writings on Goethe. The papers also contain sound recordings of Raphael's 1965 lectures given at the New York Institute of the C. G. Jung Foundation for Analytical Psychology. Photographs include portraits of Raphael and an album of snapshots of the Eckstein family and their farm in Greenwich, CT. The papers also include a scrapbook of Raphael's colored pencil drawings and a charcoal portrait of Raphael by Kahlil Gibran.
Arrangement
The papers are organized into five series: Writings and Translations, Correspondence, Lectures, Other Papers, Correspondence with Yale Collection of German Literature.
Authors -- 20th Century; German literature; Literature, Modern -- Translations; Drawings (visual works); Sound recordings; Authors; Translators; Faber du Faur, Curt von, 1890-1966; Gibran, Kahlil, 1883-1931; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Faust); Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961; Raphael, Alice, 1887-1975 ( Goethe and the philosophers stone); Schreiber, Carl F. (Carl Frederick), 1886-1960; Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
- Writings and Translations, 1918-1969; Series I; 5.63; (14 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I, Writings and Translations is arranged into four subseries: Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust', Other Writings, Translations, and Writings by Others.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains drafts of Raphael's writings and translations of selected works by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe. Drafts of Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust' are accompanied by reports written by Graham Munson and H. Popper, and a letter from Munson regarding the book. Other writings include drafts of Raphael's writings on Goethe and Thomas Mann, and portion of a memoir.
  Translations contains holograph and typescript drafts of Raphael's translation of Goethe's Faust: A Tragedy Part One and Faust: A Tragedy Part Two. Drafts are heavily annotated and corrected by Raphael and William A. Speck and Carl Schreiber, who assisted Raphael in her translation. An acting version of Faust: A Tragedy Part One included in the subseries is based on Raphael's translation. Other translations are The Parable and The Inferno of Dante Alighieri. Writings by others contains four drafts, including a writing on Historisch-kritische Nachrichten von Italien by J.J. Volkmann.
  The working title for Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust' was Goethe and the Philosopher's Stone: A Psychological Interpretation.
  - Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust'
    - Volumes 1-2, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Includes 1956 report on book, and letter to Raphael from Graham Munson, and illustrations
    - "Typed version submitted to Princeton Press," volumes 1-2, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
      Includes 1906 and circa 1935 bookplates designed by Raphael in Berlin; accompanied by Raphael letter fragment
    - "Report on Goethe and the Philosopher's Stone" by H. Popper with handwritten notes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Other writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "The Beloved Returns by Thomas Mann," draft, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    - "Goethe: A Symbol for Modern Man," drafts, typescripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "In Memorium," draft, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Regards the death of her cat
    - "Joseph Conrad's Faust: A criticism of Joseph Conrad's work Victory ," draft, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "My House Being Now Asleep: A Texas Memoir," and excerpt "From the Texan Memoir of Alice Raphael," drafts, typescript, 1966 November 15 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "She of the Flames," draft, typescript, 1930 February (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "The Things that Are," draft, handwritten, typescript and photocopy, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
    - Untitled writing on Goethe, 1944 May 16 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Translations
    This subseries is arranged under three headings: Faust: A Tragedy Part One, Faust: A Tragedy Part Two; and Other Translations. Drafts of Faust: A Tragedy Part One are arranged by Raphael's assigned draft numbers.
    - Faust: A Tragedy Part One
      - "Translator's preface," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - "A Note on Faust Translations," essay by Carl F. Schreiber, print version, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - "Introduction to newest edition of Mrs. Raphael's translation of Faust," draft by Raphael, typescript carbon, 1955 August (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Drafts, holograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
        Includes "Walpurgisnacht"
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Drafts, typescript, corrected
        - One and five, 1918-1919; 1923-1924 (Box 5, Folder 24-25)
        - Five, fragment, and six, 1923-1924 (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
        - Seven, eight, and nine, 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 28-30)
        - Ten, twelve and thirteen, 1930, undated (Box 8, Folder 31-33)
        - Fifteen, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 34)
        - Fragment, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 35-44)
        - Proofs, corrected, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 45-47)
        - Proofs, corrected, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 48-51)
      - "Faust: An Acting Version Adapted from the Metrical Translation of Goethe's Faust by Alice Raphael", 1922 (Box 12, Folder 52)
      - Acting version, prepared by Frank McMullan and Alois Nagler, typescript carbon, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 53)
        Bound, accompanied by mounted reviews of production at Yale University
    - Faust: A Tragedy Part Two
      - Draft, typescript and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 12, Folder 54)
      - Draft, typescript and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 55)
      - Draft, includes "Helena Interlude", typescript, holograph, and typescript photocopy, corrected, 1962-1969 (Box 13, Folder 56-59)
        Includes holograph note of dedication to Speck
    - Other translations
      - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, draft fragment, typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 60)
      - The Parable, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 61)
  - Writings by others
    - "Ist er in Wendelust/Scheffender Freude nah," draft, unidentified author, typescript, annotated, undated (Box 14, Folder 62)
    - "Prolegomena to the Study of Greek Religion," draft, unidentified author, typescript, annotated, undated (Box 14, Folder 63)
    - Untitled writing on Historisch-kritische Nachrichten von Italien by J.J. Volkmann, draft, typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 64)
    - Untitled writing, unidentified author, draft, typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 65)
- Correspondence, 1921-1969; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  This series is organized into two subseries: Carl Gustav Jung Correspondence and Correspondence Arranged and Annotated by Alice Raphael.
  The series contains letters from Carl Gustav Jung to Alice Raphael regarding his theory of analysis and Raphael's attempts to publish her book, Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone: Symbolical Patterns in 'The Parable' and the Second Part of 'Faust'. Jung's letters are often brief.
  The bulk of the correspondence regards Raphael's translations and her efforts to publish Faust: A Tragedy Part One and Part Two. Primary correspondents are Carl Schreiber and various publishers. Among the correspondents are Goethe scholars offering criticism of her work. The correspondence also includes one letter from Kahlil Gibran and one letter from Thomas Mann.
  Raphael arranged, bound and annotated the correspondence after Curt von Faber du Faur's death in 1966 and in preparation for the donation of her papers to Yale University. Raphael added to the correspondence until 1969. Binders were disassembled during processing and binder labels are transcribed as folder titles. Throughout the correspondence, Raphael is often addressed by her married name of Eckstein.
  Correspondence can also be found in Series VII, Correspondence with Yale Collection of German Literature.
  - Carl Gustav Jung letters, 1928-1961 (Box 15, Folder 66)
    Accompanied by photograph of Jung, Jung's memorial service program, and a clipping
  - Correspondence arranged and annotated by Alice Raphael
    Arranged according to sequence assigned by Raphael.
    - Faust: A Tragedy Part One translation and theater production, 1921-1949, 1961-1967 (Box 15, Folder 67)
    - Faust: A Tragedy Part One translation; The Parable; and Goethe and the Philosopher's Stone, 1958-1965 (Box 15, Folder 68)
    - Second publishing of Faust: A Tragedy Part One and publication of The Parable, 1949-1964 (Box 15, Folder 69-70)
    - Reactions to Faust: A Tragedy Part One translation, The Parable, and Goethe and the Philosopher's Stone, 1930-1965 (Box 15, Folder 71-72)
      Accompanied by Faust: A Tragedy Part One translation book boards; includes letters from Thomas Mann and Kahlil Gibran
    - Other correspondence, 1930-1951 (Box 15, Folder 73)
    - From Wilson Follet and Yale University Press, 1922-1924 (Box 15, Folder 74)
    - From Wilson Follet and Yale University Press regarding the Faust I translation, 1925 (Box 15, Folder 75-76)
      Includes draft, typescript, corrected by Follett
    - Regarding The Things That Are; and Mark van Doren's seventy-fifth birthday, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 77)
- Lectures, 1965; Series III; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 23 contains audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Untitled lecture given at Smith College, draft, typescript, 1936 February 27 (Box 17, Folder 78)
  - Lectures derived from Goethe and the Philosophers' Stone, given at the New York Institute of the C. G. Jung Foundation for Analytical Psychology
    - Description of lectures and Goethe and the Philosopher's Stone, undated (Box 17, Folder 79)
    - Lecture 1, draft, typescript, circa 1965 (Box 17, Folder 80)
      Accompanied by institute programs
    - Sound recordings
      - Lecture 1, 1965 April 22; 1; 01:27:16; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002104611398)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Lecture 2, 1965 April 29; 1; 01:10:28; A high amount of background noise and hum can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002104611406)
      - Lecture 3, 1965 May 6; 1; 01:35:34; The program is distorted at times. A high amount of hum can be heard. The speed of the tape fluctuates at the end of the program. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002104611414)
      - Lecture 4, 1965 May 13; 1; 01:29:02; A high amount of hum and background noise can be heard on the tape. The speed of the tape fluctuates at about 42:00 and again at the end of the program. The volume decreases from about 43:00 until the end of the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002104611422)
      - Lecture 5, 1965 May 20; 1; 01:31:27; High background noise and a high amount of hum can be heard. Static can be heard on the tape. Speed fluctuations can be heard at about 52:30. The volume gradually decreases from about 52:50 until the end of the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 23, Item barcode 39002104611380)
- Other Papers, 1917-1930, undated; Series IV; 4.38; (4 boxes) + 1 framed portrait
  - Photographs, 1917-1930
    - Four photographs of Alice Raphael and one photograph of portrait by Kahlil Gibran, 1917, 1930, undated (Box 18, Folder 86)
    - Photograph album of Eckstein family and farm in Greenwich, CT, 1927 May
      Photographed by William Francis Weed
  - Scrapbook, 1922
    Accompanied by Raphael's 1968 notes on the scrapbook and her friendship with Curt von Faber du Faur; contains color pencil drawings by Raphael; three pieces for voice and piano by Raphael; "Now Like a Lantern" song, words by Alice Raphael and piano music by A. Walter Kramer; pamphlet on Kramer's music; and signed piano music by Louis Gruenberg; and commercial phonodisc sound recording of solo voice and piano. Scrapbook disassembled during processing.
  - Portrait of Raphael by Kahlil Gibran, charcoal, undated; 25 x 30 inches, framed
- Correspondence with Yale Collection of German Literature, 1928-1977; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  This series is arranged chronologically by correspondent.
  Correspondence with Yale Collection of German Literature contains correspondence between Alice Raphael and curators of the Yale Collection of German Literature. The correspondence documents Raphael's relationships with the curators as she worked on her translations of Faust: A Tragedy Part One and Two, her work as a Goethe scholar, and the donation of her books and papers to Yale University. Correspondence between curator Christa Sammons and Raphael's daughter Alice Wolff regards additional papers donated to Yale after Raphael's death.
  - Schreiber, Carl, 1928-1939, undated (Box 19, Folder 87-94)
  - von Faber du Faur, Curt, 1956-1966 (Box 19, Folder 95-97)
  - Dejon, Hedwig S., 1967-1970 (Box 19, Folder 98)
  - Letters from Alice Wolff to Christa Sammons, 1975-1977 (Box 19, Folder 99)
- Oversize
  - Photograph album of Eckstein family and farm in Greenwich, CT, 1927 May (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, 1922 (Box 21, Folder 100-114)
  - Scrapbook, 1922 (Box 22, Folder 115-118)